{
  "reference_number": "1204",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "As scientists learn more about the causes, extent, rate of change and implications of climate change, the problem becomes\n increasingly urgent. We don't have the luxury of time in which to stop carbon and other emissions, especially as the rest of the world\n\n has to compensate for having a climate-change-denying lunatic in the White House."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "We don't have time to be half-hearted in combatting climate change. We have to go all the way as quickly as possible if the planet is to\n survive."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Carbon trading as a system has already proved to be vulnerable to fraud. We have already been sucked in. We should not repeat our\n\n stupidity. The Government should instigate carbon taxes on polluters with the money used to help people whose homes are made\n uninhabitable because of climate change. In our area, we already have houses being washed into the sea. Insurance companies\n refuse to insure any homes that are vulnerable so people walk away with nothing. As the scale and rate of destruction increase, we\n\n are going to have huge numbers of homeless people if there is no government system in place. This will inevitably lead to social\n unrest. These people have poured their life savings into their homes and suddenly they have nowhere to go. The scale is already\n significant here and people still have to pay rates on uninhabitable homes unless the councils choose otherwise. There is no law that\n\n says councils have to stop charging rates in these circumstances. In our case, in Buller, councils, in approving and supporting coal\n mining, and in making sure that ordinary people cannot complain about breaches of consents, are ensuring that the maximum\n\n amount of coal is being stripped out as fast as possible. They are actually exacerbating the problem then rating damaged homes and\n charging for consents for people to build bunds to try to save their homes (as has happened at Granity). The councils profit on all\n counts. It's disgusting. Only the Government can put a stop to this. So far, governments have exhibited a complete lack of interest in\n\n protecting West Coasters against coal mining."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But only to make it more stringent."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But only upwards."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We obviously need to consider the economy but we also have to consider that our great-grandchildren may live in a very small\n\ncountry with its borders overwhelmed by people fleeing from sea-level rise, drought etc. You need to work with scientists, economist,\nsocial-sector experts - all areas of expertise really. The problem is so big it's hard to get one's head around it."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I think the ETS is a stupid idea. Have a carbon tax because where else are you going to get the money to rehome hundreds, maybe\nthousands, of people."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I think this is a separate issue."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But remember that some of us are already trying to survive climate change. It's urgent."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Government needs to act instead of mucking around in endless afternoon teas."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I do not want my name published. Living here is dangerous enough for a 'tree-hugger' without this."
    }
  ]
}
